sh
so if we continue
B following from the previous
discussion how do you breathe
how you doing
that inhale and you exhale how you
inhale how do you
exhale how do you lift your arms
how do you stand up how do you sit
down you intend to do that you intend to
do it yeah but is there anything in
between the intention and the action of
doing
it how does that does that
intention where does that intention go
does it enter the body and move your
arm I intend to breathe and breathe
out where is the intention where's the
body where's the breath in this
case you know the answer we'll be
talking about in some deeper
breathe in take a long
breath take a short breath take a
forceful Breath Take a light
breath where's the intention where's the
breathing say the intention is
underneath
mhm but is it
though that's exactly how you would
start but is it
underneath underneath
what underneath the
breath but what is that intention when
you look at
it it's an image of the physical
breathing so if there is no image of the
physical breathing there will be no
intention
so why does it feel like underneath
that cuz it does
because of the Assumption of there being
a relationship between the intention and
yes but there is a relationship so you
start with a relationship that's
obviously wrongly
assumed but can people tell me details
about that wrong assumption
particulars is this what
um I mean this is I think what I meant
with we were talking last time when I
said there's like this kind of blurring
of boundaries
between
the the intention to breathe that kind
of makes the body Brea do the breathing
and then you feel the body breathing and
you feel like you
have or the intention has caused the
breathing yes yes and that's obviously
not something you're actively thinking
no but it is implied in every bodily
action well it's implied for example
through through regarding your intention
is under something under the breath that
already carries so that's why that overlap that
carries so that's why that overlap that
cannot be mhm overlap of the
domains but you start with that you have
to start with that you start with what
it actually and even if it somebody
describes it differently so might say I
don't feel like it's under there I feel
like it's in here either way see you
realize any positionality so to speak in regard
any positionality so to speak in regard
to the breath assumes a relationship
with it
it
yeah but assumes breath to come out of
the intention the intention so in other
words your
intention ciously not knowing that it's actually
ciously not knowing that it's actually
impossible takes up the
body through assuming
it's breathing so to speak in the same
sense your thoughts take up your mouth
when you
speak because when you think and you say
what you
think the implicit assumption is that
it's those thoughts have become these
words have descended and turned into the
sounds there's this as I said kind of
directionality from you outward and same
with the breath but actually
there well that's
impossible that's the whole point of the
practice is to completely remove any
traces of that directionality that
implies ownership and me here doing
these things through the body through
the speech through the mental
intentions so how do you then breathe so
the attention is not
actually cannot actually descend into
the physical domain canot actually take
it
up how' you
breathe how can you not forget to
breathe I mean you can forget about
breathing but you never forget to
breathe it's not that you are doing it
it is happening so who's doing it then
yeah it's not you who's doing it you
can't be doing it so asking who's doing
it is it so who or what is doing
it it's unavoidably there something is
doing it yeah intention is doing it
which is unavoidable how how can oh
sorry the body sorry yeah the body so
the body is doing
it in it's Bly
domain on account of your intention in
its intention
domain but see even that that goes kind
thinking if I say the body is doing it
if you just say the body is doing it
then obviously can be
misunderstood but if you say it at the
end of all this questioning then it's
hopefully clear what we mean by
that so presence of
intention makes the body
breathe but there's no relationship
between the two mhm those those two
domains don't connect there is no Live
Wire that connects the intentional
domain that touches the body and then
snaps it into breathing it's just
intention to breathe it's here and body
breathing it's
here and there's nothing in
between there's no
directionality um overlap Connection in
between it's just your intention to
breathe exists in its own domain
directed in its own Direction
simultaneous to that there is the body
corresponding to so the
relationship if there were to be a
relationship it's inconceivable by you
you are left out from that
relationship but see even thinking that
there is an external relationship
between them that I'm not privy to can
become your assumption
so it's really the only way to reach the
point of not assuming the impossible
relationship between the two internally
is to undo
any uh notion tested assumptions of
overlap of directionality and then
what's left well is the conscious body in name
left well is the conscious body in name
and form
externally I the domain of the breathing
body and everything else external name
and form
so that's really the training of
an it's under mind that very first very
subtle very easily done because it's
already your starting point connection
between my and that's the whole point of
the intentional those steps in an where
intentionally breathing like this or
like that you're not shying away from
intentional involv mement with the
breath once obviously the proper mind
recollected and knowledge of the breath
is established because you want to
hammer it in that no matter how forceful
how determined how intentional your
intention is it remains fully enclosed
within own domain and the body doesn't
even know about
it but look it's happening because of
the intention well yes that still
doesn't mean they
connect not in any measurable Way by you
internally
and then you stretch the same
principle and actually once you start
undoing or seeing through the gratuitous
Assumption of this
directionality from mind intention the
breath comes you realize the breathing
is always underneath the body the domain
of the body is always underneath
underneath your domain of intentions
underneath the domain of your feelings
underneath the domain of your
mind J and that's exactly why you start
stretching the same
principle breathing in like this I'll
experience the body breathing in like
this breathing out like this I'll
experience the feeling I'll experience
the mind I'll experience the Damas the
images because if the body is
inaccessible
underneath and the correspondence of
bodily actions and presence of mental
reactions has no measurable D
directionality overlap connection not
even a
trace then there
absolutely in the very core there is
nothing that you can deem here but this
came from
me this has originated from
me because it completely undermines the
perception of any
Mastery because you realize even when I
intend I only know it worked because the
body over there bre it happened to do it
basically happened to do it on account
of this and even that you only kind of
know indirectly like is in you have the
yeah feel of it happening and then kind
of underneath that that's the point and
that's exactly why well at some point
you will stop breathing despite how
strong you will intend to breathe you
will not be able to I was going to say
actually because I was this something I
was thinking about
like I don't know how to put this okay
so um let's say with um
speaking like it's very it's quite
clear that at the moment when I'm speak
when I speak when I actually speak I can
only do it by kind of looking past the
actual thoughts and I was starting to notice
thoughts and I was starting to notice
that there is it feels like there's
corresponding thing with the intention
to breathe like if I actually become if
I'm very aware well that's what you're
training against your training is
supposed to undo
that that cuz yes of course every
intentional involvement will make you
look past intentional to the thing and
that's why it just naturally leads to
that assumption MH of the physicality
the connection with it that
whole um proliferation that takes place
on account of
simply not knowing that those things are
not connectable um so it's like developing
connectable um so it's like developing
the perception of
that well developing the practice say of
the intentional breathing whereby
intention does not spill out into the ju
opposed physical domain that exists in
its own
extent then the perceptions of that
physical domain that exists in in so
extent you use to undermine any other
intentional involvement not necessarily
in regard to
breathing in any in regard to any
feeling that's present in regard to any
mind state in regard to any pressure
there is the body breathing underneath
it and just to the extent that you know
that correctly to that extent the domain
that's pressuring you to take up the
directionality to follow it it's kind of
frozen so to speak you freeze it in its
own extent even if the pressure remains
extent even if the pressure remains
within it you are not the one pressured
so practicing in regard to these four
things there will be
nothing but there will be no more there
will be no uh place left for any assumed
overlaps and connections to
exist so it would be like that similar
in the suit as a skill monk is like a
like a butcher that cuts up a cow and
completely clearly fully separates pile
it's meat tendon bones organs clearly
and you realize oh yeah they were piled
up together but they were never
one with each other or or blending one
into another always clearly separate
things obviously people often
misunderstand that as some sort of
dry intellectual analysis of elements
but if you approach it phenologically
you realize no those domains of
phenomena the Aggregates of phenomena
and you see them in its own extent in
its full
extent completely independent of each
other that's why it's the five hips it's
on one hip doesn't matter how much it's
heaped up you will always
discern Rupa
V and anything in this
layer that belongs to SAA goes to Saia
it's understood under a Saia domain
anything belongs on the V is understood
on the V domain doesn't matter the
specifics to intentionally breathing
differently long short knowingly but not
for the sake of
breathing but for the sake of fully kind
of dragging out an implicit
assumption that at least some degree of
your intentionality flows into the
physical and makes you
breathe so the result of that
is a perception of complete AR
confinement but uh that's not as
unpleasant as if it were to be
discovered through the contemplation of
death or a
subba because that body that domain of
body breathing there always has been
like that independent of you having a
life of its own so to
speak neither good nor bad and then H
it's fairly
neutral so Al you're completely confined
within it you realize you're confined
within the neutrality and that's not a
problem
really and same as I was
saying in our telegram group the uh
if you feel
undermined by that domain that's
inaccessible that's now being
unblurred whose J the position has been
clearly outlined there is no means of accessing
outlined there is no means of accessing
it and if you feel anxi or something on
account of being undermined you realize
well that's
undermined the anxious CH is equally
undermined by this
thing oh but what if then doubt starts
arising that's undermined by the
enduring breathing that reveals the domain of
breathing that reveals the domain of
jaos physicality
just basically like
the complete un
management of like just undermining
whether you want it or not regardless of
whatever can possibly yeah come
up including like the feelings on
account of that very yeah yeah exactly
yeah
so I was asking we were in some recently
talking about this with the among there
what was that
Su cuz I was saying I I remember there's
a su where would have
compared a v to a bar that connects
things and I think said I think majima
28 or something H remember but we did
mention in a few talks back right you
was saying it was those well no no no no
this was different this was like the
cryptic lines about the
anill with KN and then he pulls a bar
and then pulls this out of this thing
that he's digging up and
basically that's Thea the
bar that sort
of one end lays on your intentional
domain another end lays on your physical
domain cuz you don't know that it
can't so removing the connection between
those domains those
fields keeps the fields remain intact as
they always were
actually but that entire internal
directionality that implies ownership
that implies Eternal as mind all of that
that's just
gone that's why I'm just thinking that's
why probably it's like it's quite
important to actually to start
with how it genuinely feels or like the
the the sense of the
connection that is there rather than
well that's the only way you can start
if you're honest that's what I mean like
you can't if you have start approaching
it with your wrong views then yeah it's
going to be like a some system of there
are no things there's no connection and
now I must like see that there are no in
reality there is no connection con I
have to kind of and all of that is going
to leave no in reality there is
connection yeah that is your
reality so you want to undermine it not
through your abstract thought and
developing systems and the ideas of
structure or external things because of
which this all is no you undermine
it through the practice we just
described so obviously presumably person
is withdrawn from the
uality correct sensor strength that's
already a form of undermining then on
top of that
any any perceptions that you have of
your own physicality are undermined by
the domain of body breathing and
intentions any state of CH whether it's
elated depressed afraid happy all that
second to the jaapos domain of
inaccessible domain of the body
breathing any images any thoughts you realize oh
any images any thoughts you realize oh
they are
simultaneous but they exist in its own
domain and the point is well another
Point worth mentioning is is you don't
have to be trying now to catch or police
all these little intentions like scratch
my face or I don't know adjust the
seating position or something cuz that
yes that too carries the implication but
that's not that's not the reason for the
implication of the connection of the
domain it's the intentions rooted in
greed aversion delusion are the sources
of the ignorance of the bridge
so you undo those then all these other
ones will sew themselves
out thinking that as well like there's
no it's like in the same way there's no
problem with breathing in the sense it's
not a it's a completely neutral action
but just by virtue of all of these
other actions being done around every
possible action carries the same
implication so you use a neutral action
that you can that observe quote unquote
while in with a calm mind that is not
occupied by hindrances in order
to like uproot or kind of see that
assumption in in real life and somebody
who is doing that they might even feel
like too much of a craving on kind of
sense of Duty to see it correctly mhm
it's like well even then you continue
breathing and you undermine that you
don't stop it because it feels
unpleasant it feels unpleasant not
because of the breathing but because of
your expectation in regard to
it so I must see like this I say like
this and then CH is getting upset
getting affected getting
pressured it's like oh but breathing is
down there in its own domain inaccessible
there in its own domain inaccessible
underneath all of this
mess so it's not about stopping the mess
getting rid of it it's about undermining
it with well correctly
discerned basis what's underneath so
with correctly correctly developed Yara
you would undermine it because it's the
yis of whatever you're attending that
recognizes the physicality of the body
breathing and that's how it goes away
the Mind comes down
the thoughts on account of being
pressured by that mind come down as
well like how the simil
says when the rain comes and just the
dust that was in the air just
settles and that was the comparison
for so it's through indirect means you
settle the dust not through catching the
particles of dust one by one as they fly
around
that it's reminding me of another thing
that like last time you were
asking just even in Broad terms like how
do you start doing anap panti and what
was thinking was that probably the most
what I would say is like the most
accurate way would be
basically like the point is you need to
be restraining your bodily intentions
restraining your verbal intentions
dwelling inclusion restraining your
mental intentions and while you're doing
all of that it's not really that useful
to try to do an aanti it's more like
well once you're doing all of that and
now you kind of recognize is you're able
there's a thought pressuring you and
you're able to not give it attention
what you find yourself with yeah is
basically the things you can be mindful
the reason for that is
because if you do it before your
intentions would not have
been softened to put it that way
enough so they're still way too
charged with craving with this with that
so then when you turn that to
breathing you're just going to be doing
it again through the same
perversion but if you would have been
withdrawn from our whole states
restrained that's
already as I said uh removing that that
stiffness of that
direction so then yes you might still
have traces of it and you start doing
the breathing and you're still doing
them with as I said intentions of
expectations and craving involved but
there is enough space through that
looseness of these intentions to now see
them see the underlying body that
unconnected with it just exist over
there my intention goes up up here and
as I said the result of it seeming
result of it is simultaneous body
breathing down
there and then of course then you
cultivate more make much of as a s to
say encourage monks to keep doing it
because it will just be p in of layer by
layer by
layer of
that connection assumption which is an
assumption
yeah yeah that's exactly like I think we
mentioned last time I don't know it was
recorded or
afterwards but you know the
anapanasati brings the Sati panas to
fulfillment which brings the four right
strivings which brings seven
Enlightenment factors which is a
different way of saying it PU you
completely and andati was thought to at
and andati was thought to at
least they would quite clearly describe
that but then there are
sutas where it said that
saatana can be thought as a means of
those who don't have the right
view develop
it but not any Tom Dick and Harry
without a right view is like the monks
that would have already been living
restrained with patima withdrawn from un
wholesome States guarding their sense
doors moderating eating dwelling in
seclusion but still don't have the right
View and that's exactly what you said
like if you haven't
met these aspects of the gradual
training then doing saatana will be done
with your craving so it's not
saatana so that's the only suit that
mentions every other instance of saatana
or anapanasati was basically thought to
the monks they already had the right
view but the Su does specifically say
that you could teach it even to those
monks that don't have the right view so
you realize okay they they don't have
the right view but they would have lived
pretty trained already
in softening those rigid assume
directions of their ownership
intentionality craving so it's like okay
so they already have a degree of
Yono degree of Y so now get them to do
this contrasting practice to undermine
it further and to then just see it how
it should be
seen but people often take that suta to
say see you don't have to be a
so and then Laton to that
technicality ignoring the major
technicality that they're not fulfilling
I they're not a monk they're not
celibate they're not withdrawn from
sensuality they don't dwell in
seclusion so if we want to be
technical those are the absolute
necessities and you could see as I said
because it's that's already the
beginning of
satana even if you don't specifically
are doing clarification and and and
discernment of these four domains body
feeling um mind and thoughts
by not following sensuality at its face
value by not following by being salate
by being withdrawn from distractions
quite important by dwelling secluded
physically secluded you are already
highlighting these things that's why you
be you will be able to recognize it
because if you haven't built up these
these things well there's nothing for
you to recognize because it's not there
but yeah that was all like in relation
to saatana but I think when it comes to
anati that's even bit more specific so
I I don't think You' be able to do it
without a Right View at all even if he
were perfectly well maybe theoretically
I suppose there might be a monk
that's quite established in yis so with
drawn but just just so close but not
seeing it and then working grinding
through the
anapanasati and the pain of undermining
his sense of self through that might be
enough but he might be his own cing
for the expectations of the
result it might be worth mentioning um
when you sit down to do an
aanti do you need to close your eyes oh
absolutely not there's no such thing as
meditation with closed eyes even in the
broadest sense of meditation that we
would have used MH certainly no
meditation in terms of a technique that
you do
but um somebody could take the
description yes you sit down and you
play in the wood I you breathe like this
you breede like this so to undermine
your own intentionality in regard to
breathing they can take that as
something they do because it is a form
of doing but that whole idea of eyes
closed I think that probably came from
some Yogi practices that Tred to wrap
their head around the Buddhist genre but
couldn't quite understand it so
mystified it themselves it's just you go
into fantasy world doesn't matter you
self hypnotize you read any any any self
hypnosis instruction and uh it all it's all
instruction and uh it all it's all
exactly that you and actually there was
I remember in Sri Lanka there was this
uh the common meditation instruction you
is like you look about 3 or 4 feet in
front of you for a brief for a period of
time and then you kind of sort of start
quinting and you let your right and then
you close your eyes and get into your
casin or meditation object or whatever
and I found these uh self Hypno hypnosis
techniques it was exactly the same so
look like I don't know a meter ahead of
you and then start intending your eye
eyelids being heavy feeling them is
really heavy until your eyes naturally
close and then start Distributing these
energies of your breath through the
different parts of your body and feeling
it and like and it was just like
again not not that they were um they
obviously thought it's a good self
hypnosis it's a good
idea and then you entered this hypnotic
State and it was actually in a book
about hypnosis yeah and uh they thought it was
hypnosis yeah and uh they thought it was
a great thing to deal with suffering to
numb yourself to it to distract yourself
from it so yeah the whole idea of
meditating with your eyes closed rightly
or wrongly whatever meditation is it's
well that wrong
destruction well there is absolutely no
way that you would remain the clarity of
perception in regard to the this
different domains that we talk about if
you start closing your eyes absolutely
yeah because you can do that almost just
almost as a kind of a natural assumption
even if you you know try and do all of
this you no that already practically speaking
you no that already practically speaking
that already divorces you from any any
correct basis
yeah it kind of assumes that the problem
is the object like in the in what I
perceive like I will be distracted but
it certainly it enables imagination a
lot more when your eyes are closed the
mind the thoughts just pick up the
energies just flow and you start you
start basically dreaming yeah while
you're awake um and um no no it's absolutely
awake um and um no no it's absolutely
not a question of eyes
closed and so yeah you can it's a it's a
way to imagine fantasy world you imagine
fantasy world much better much easier
with your eyes closed open y yeah
keeping your eyes open just keeps things
so mundane yeah exactly exactly and
that's quite boring and depressing
actually yeah you have the kind
of doubt am I doing it right and the
Eyes Are Open you're forced to kind of
be awake to that whole thing if you
close your eyes it's like just you can
imagine like breath coming into your
neck coming running down
just this way and then you building up
this fantasy world of these breath
energies yeah that now become your
views not yeah like we we call it
fantasy and hypnosis and TRS and and and
dismiss it but if you actually don't if
you think it's a valid thing all those I
mean the hypnosis and self- induced
transes are real things as such it's not
that it's not real which means if you
don't see it for what it is experiencing
those things will just be now fueling
your views so you're going to develop
these views of these objective existing
energies and kundalinis and stuff over
there that you just need to tap
into all driven by your by your like as
I said hypnotic induced fantasy that
made your body feel like it's not there
and light and energy and the perception
of light it's always the perception of
light your head fills with light I read
that through these Kundalini accounts so
some contemporary Jana teaches is just
this this whole like like the light the
light and like you the the the rushing
sounds in your ears and stuff it's like
how is that different than any sound
that you hear how is that different than
any light that you perceive why is it so
special well it's special because it
just feels Supernatural it just feels
different and different is good so
basically the measure then of your
success and your accomplishment is just
novelty as I said induced but novelty
runs out so you have to keep doing more
than more because it will become
mundane but I think for more people it's
the view that's implicit that they would
have freed themselves from suffering for
the period of time when they were
unaware of their suffering when they're
una unaware of the inherent undermining
of their human existence that's
constantly undermined by the
independence of the aggregates that
there is absolutely no place for
safety four mountains coming crushing
every there is no like not even a
millimeter you can hide well you develop
the idea of the ecstatic TR that's
outside of the
Aggregates and it's like oh yeah that's
that's my safety see this is actually
outside of the Aggregates I know the
Buddha said there is nothing outside of
the Aggregates but this Consciousness is
outside of the Aggregates because it's
just so special please don't take it
away from me
and then you do have the factual
physical lightness and and and and
extreme pleasure in your body on account
of the the beautiful hypnosis that you
just L yourself into and that's the
validity of the reality of this belief
that I have now cuz that was factually
experienced you know it's like like
those Evangelical preachers when they
sort of people up in big groups and they
start feeling this this Roar of the
whole stadium and they said you see that
what you feel I like yeah I mean we all
factually feel it well that's Jesus but
okay must be because I have factually
felt that and now he provided a little
input as to what that really was and now
I hold the belief that I did experience
the Divine in the reality you go any
Divine in the reality you go any
football match you're going to
experience the same thing at least in
Eastern Europe
right when when thousand people are
screaming the same thing it just feels
like a massive war tribe and even if
you're completely disinterested you
going to feel
it the Roar the the the the sound the
vibration the mess yeah it's like if you
take the approach from the sutas you
realize doesn't matter the novelty
doesn't matter how new how big how great
how lofty experience of feeling is the
lofty experience of feeling is the
experience of feeling perception
perception is there Consciousness
Consciousness is there there's nothing
special and that's how you completely
experience this passion to there's
nothing special in any form of thees in
the most Divine to Heavens it's still
the five grates in the worst of the
hells it's still the five
grates equal dispassion well that's why
you won't appear in any of those places
it's like that unawareness like you can
even just say okay well I don't even
want novelty experiences or anything but
I and and it's not wrong to say that
meditation even correct meditation is a
kind of a form of
relaxing yeah but there's a there's big
fat line just relaxing and and and and
entering a TR well ex exact but that's
exactly what I'm my point basically is
that like
relaxing always is basically associated
with unawareness so it's not um people don't
unawareness so it's not um people don't
know where to when to stop yeah yeah
they stop through relaxing and then they
start very much doing it so they they
become as I said
hypnotized but you relax as we discussed
in the previous video only to to the
extent that it was active if you start
relaxing more than that that becomes
your new activity so you are not
peaceful you're not calm and you
certainly won't be relaxed although you
might feel very pleasant and you
completely be unaware and kind of that's
the closest you can get to feeling
relaxed